Joe: Let's now look at how the terms
‘neurodiverse’ and ‘neurotypical’
are used in relation to autism.
The study of the human brain
shows a significant overlap
between fields of neurology and
psychiatry in the understanding of
how the brain affects behaviours.
New terminologies often become part of
common usage to define the differences in
how the world is perceived by different
people and two commonly used terms are
‘neurodivergent’ and ‘neurotypical’.
Beth: The term ‘neurodiverse’ applies
to individuals who are ‘neurodivergent’.
The conditions of ADHD, Autism,
Dyspraxia, and Dyslexia make up
neurodiversity, and neuro-differences
are recognised as a social category.
As a concept, neurodiversity has been
around for a while and those with
conditions like ADHD and Autism aren't
seen as ‘abnormal’ they're just different.
The term neurodiverse is used to
describe a variety of conditions
related to cognitive abilities
especially relevant for those Autism.
Neurodiverse individuals often struggle
with soft skills, especially ones
that apply to ‘social interactions’
and find physical behaviours like
standing too close to someone or
speaking too loudly distressing.
Neurodiversity is an idea that takes into
account variations in the human brain
regarding learning, mood, attention,
sociability, and other mental functions
and doesn’t regarded these as abnormal
or unhealthy but as differences
to be understood and worked with.
Neurodiversity reflects the idea
that Autism is not a mental health
problem and rejects the medical model
of disability and whilst not all
individuals with Autism apply this term
to themselves it can help more people
on the spectrum to live fuller lives.
Joe: The term ‘neurotypical’ started
to be used around the same time as
neurodiversity as a means of describing
those who don’t display autistic or
other ‘atypical ‘patterns of thoughts
or behaviour, a way of describing
people without any particular condition.
Neurotypical describes individuals
who display ‘typical’ intellectual
and cognitive development and are
on the whole social and thrive
from interacting with each other.
They acquire physical, verbal,
intellectual, and social skills usually
at a specific pace and meet standardly
accepted milestones for development.
Neurotypical people also display commonly
accepted physical behaviours such as
being able to speak whilst modulating
their volume and don’t find such things as
maintaining eye contact distressing, and
can function without becoming overloaded
by stimuli in distracting situations.
Beth: However the term ‘typical’ can
vary from person to person and within
cultures, also some individuals can
experience an overlap in what is
considered neurodiverse and neurotypical.
Joe: But the meaning of both terms is
constantly evolving, the term neurotypical
is an improvement over the term
‘normal’ but how do we define typical.
An individual is unique by nature,
and creating a dividing line between
those who are Neuro-diverse and those
who are Neurotypical is not easy,
but should it even be necessary?